the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to
perform Hello friends I'm Dr Andy Galpin
I'm a professor of Kinesiology in the
center for sport performance at Cal
State of Fullerton in today's show we're
going to be talking about lactate or how
many of you probably think of it lactic
acid now I know when I say those words
you immediately start thinking about
things like exercise and muscle and
fatigue soreness and and reducing
exercise performance and that all is
true kind of in fact as we're going to
lay out the overwhelming perceptions and
thoughts about what lactate or lactic
acid really are and what they're doing
are massively false in fact I'll spill
the beans right now lactate is in no
form or fashion cause of your muscle
fatigue it actually does quite the
opposite it preserves muscle performance
we'll get into all that stuff later in
fact I actually think that highlights
why I wanted to have this conversation
or do this episode is because it's high
time we start really understanding what
lactate truly is and how it's
functioning in our body it has
classically been thought of as this
waste product something that you don't
want to round uh something that you want
to avoid at all cost or manage or
mitigate whenever possible and the
reality of it is it has a number of
widespread benefits across your entire
physiological landscape let me give you
a couple examples of what I'm talking
about lactate is known to stimulate a
molecule called pgc1 Alpha this is
involved in any metabolically active
tissue and any part of your body and it
is directly responsible for
mitochondrial
biogenesis this is another way of saying
by increasing in utilizing more lactate
you're going to be increasing and making
more
mitochondria this is a known response
and this is obviously a positive thing
for overall health and performance but
it even goes beyond that let me give you
a couple of other examples you may not
realize for example did you know lactate
targets LX cells which are responsible
of course for testosterone in your body
it has a number of other benefits such
as bdnf so brain derived neurotropic
Factor this works directly on the
hippocampus to stimulate neurogenesis so
the growing of new neurons particularly
in your brain similar idea with a
molecule called VF which is responsible
for endothelial cells and then therefore
promoting angiogenesis so the growing of
new vasculature throughout your entire
body grin which is associated with
Hunger so lactate actually acts directly
on the hypothalamus to regulate gin and
one of the major benefits here is
suppression of appetite I don't need to
explain a lot to you there but very few
people can do a high-intensity exercise
spout where they generate a lot of
lactate and then feel extremely hungry
immediately afterwards so appetite
suppression with high lactate is a
pretty easy one to imagine I'm going to
go even further though because there's
so many more things lactate doing
whether we're talking about the liver
and the kidneys and increasing what's
called gluconeogenesis so as you'll see
later in our conversation the primary
place that we're getting the molecule or
precursors for gluconeogenesis is
lactate another benefit is its ability
to act on Osteo class and therefore play
a role in bone remodeling now I could go
on and on here and we're not quite done
yet because I want to give you a handful
of ones I'm going to Rapid Fire these
ones but lactate again has been highly
associated with positive adaptations
across your brain uh it's heavily
involved in memory and learning heart
health dehydration in fact any of you
that have ever used a ringer solution I
know exactly what I'm talking about
there cancer sep is insulin regulation
traumatic brain injuries wound healing
postsurgery recovery arthritis
inflammation gut microbiome health and
then finally overall metabolic
flexibility my guess is you had no idea
that many things were happening in
response to lactate so in order to
understand all these things what I would
love to do is spend a little time today
walking you through exactly what lactate
really is how it's created how it's
managed what role it's truly playing in
your overall physiology and then of
course at the end we will do our three
eyes which is investigation how do I
measure this stuff what should I be
paying attention to two interpret how do
I know if I'm good bad great terrible or
world record and then three intervene
how do I improve my body's ability to
produce and clear lactate so that it can
perform at its highest level regardless
of the task I'm asking my body to
perform to get us started on this
journey we're going to go all the way
back to the beginning when we initially
discovered and began to understand the
role of lactate in really all of biology
but specifically in human exercise
physiology the story really starts in
1708 when sheal found lactate in sour
milk now the term he gave it actually
roughly translates I think into milk
acid but it really persisted in this
idea of just general food space until
nearly 30 years later in 1808 when a
scientist bersus and I have tried to
pronounce this at least 200 times but
bersus really and this is a classic
story in all exercise physiology Cycles
he found that concentrations of lactate
were much higher in hunted Stags so a
deer-like creature in Europe and so it's
very clear at this point that lactate is
somehow associated with elevated stress
or exercise and we didn't really know
much past that but it seemed to be in
all of physiology at this point so we
had now crossed over from things um like
food elements and bacteria into now
human physiology so that was really a
big step up in terms of our
understanding of the relative importance
of it for living creatures now bersus
went on to do a whole bunch of other
stuff in this field in fact he was
directly responsible for the name that
you all probably recognized as a
catalyst U by studying lactate and
trying to figure out what's going on he
really came up with this idea that he
called ferments now that sounds familiar
because it is where we got fermentation
from in fact you may be starting to make
a connection in your brain which we'll
do a little bit more directly later that
really lactate and fermentation are
almost one and the same in a human
exercising muscle we call it anerobic g
olsis and lactate production in food
elements and in the food industry we
call it fermentation not exactly the
same but very very close and I'll maybe
explain that a little bit more later we
haven't really moved into the realm yet
of exercise physiology there was no real
understanding that this was happening as
a byproduct of muscular contractions or
anything like that at this time we were
still at the level of understanding what
happens when carbohydrates are used with
and without oxygen so in fact we can be
more direct here when we break down
carbohydrates for a fuel source that's
fermentation you do the same thing with
protein you we call that thing
putrification same thing happens with
fat and you call it rancidification and
so I fact you may have never made that
connection before but you ferment
carbohydrates fats go rancid and
proteins are putrified so at this point
in the story we're kind of into the mid
1800s in fact in 1843 shurter was the
first to find lactate in the blood he
actually was autopsying folks that had
died from septics and fevers and
infections and things like that and
notice during these bouts of really high
fever so we now know of course that's
really high caloric expenditure really
high need for energy high temperature
etc etc you've gone through a lot of
metabolism lactic concentrations were
really high we hadn't really Associated
this with muscle yet and certainly
hadn't done it with exercise and we were
actually at this point thinking it was
something that happened to be associated
with death the St Stags had been dying
folks these folks had been dying or dead
and that's all we knew at this point
it was another 15 years or so at the
late 1850s when they first started
finding this in the blood of actual
living people and this changed
everything in fact for the next 50 years
or so most of our breakthroughs were
from a gentleman named Lou Pastor you're
probably familiar with him and in fact
all the stuff that we do with milk and
we pasteurize it all this is from
pastor's original work and so there was
all these associations that were
floating around and then really
everything came to fruition with the
very Classic series of papers in 1907
from a combination of folks one of them
is the the authors Hopkins and Fletcher
were really the first to identify that
lactate was a byproduct of muscle
contraction and then a handful of years
go on and two very famous scientists
both whom won Nobel prizes OT meerhoff
and AV Hill put together what most
people and certainly at the
undergraduate or graduate exercise
physiology level Now understand as basic
lactate metabolism we are now
understanding things like it's coming
from car carbohydrates it's coming from
muscular contraction there's an
association between more metabolism more
lacate production and all that
fundamental stuff and while they
certainly got many things wrong meerhoff
and a hill are the ones most credited
with our basic understanding of the
differences between anerobic anerobic
metabolism and lactate being a core Cog
in that discussion in 1960 lactate
analyzers came on board and the field
exploded and one of the more fundamental
things that happened was a paper
published by waserman 1964 in which he
outlined a concept called the anerobic
threshold now what he was basically
saying there is at some point when
you're producing energy and you need
more of it you switch from aerobic into
anerobic metabolism and there's a
threshold for everyone in which you can
no longer produce energy aerobically and
you have to switch to anerobic
metabolism if I missed you with all that
stuff and you don't really know what
those terms are I promise I'm going to
come back and walk you through that all
in just one second but this concept of
the anerobic threshold from 1964
persisted for a very long time however
even waserman himself fairly recently
and a series of letters has acknowledged
that that was probably not the right
concept and the real rationale here
going all the way back to mehoff and AV
Hill was the fundamental understanding
or thought that lactate was produced as
a result of insufficient oxygen in
muscle and that's an incredibly
important Point here so I'll say it one
more time the idea at this point was you
go through Anor robic metabolism of
carbohydrates and again if you don't
know what those terms are I will walk
you through that in just one second but
you go through that anerobic metabolism
of carbohydrates and if you have enough
oxygen you'll proceed and handle the
carbohydrate just fine if you don't
that's when you generate lactate and at
remember at this point lactate was still
thought of as a negative thing as a
thought of as a cause of fatigue and so
that's really kicked off at that point
it wasn't until 1983 when a young
scientist named George Brooks launched
an idea called the lactate shuttle
hypothesis now it took him almost 17
years to really outline the entire thing
but by the 1990 or so he had fully
explained the lactate shuttle since then
the last 20 years he has just continued
to dump more and more research in
support of that such that the field
generally recognized it as while we can
continue to call this the lactate
shuttle
hypothesis it's very hard to refute at
this point now before we go too much
further I'd like to take a quick break
and thank our sponsors because they make
this show possible not only are they on
this list because they offer great
products and services but because I
actually personally love them and use
them myself today's episode is brought
to you by momentus MST make supplements
of the absolute highest quality for
example we've long known about the
numerous health and performance benefits
of fish oil I've personally been taking
it for probably 15 years or more
numerous Studies have consistently
demonstr ated positive impacts of EPA
and DHA the two primary fish oils on
everything from cardiovascular and brain
health to exercise performance and joint
pain now you can get fish oil anywhere
but personally I only use momentus
because it's never once given me a fishy
aftertaste and more importantly every
single batch is NSF tested to ensure the
lead and mercury levels are undetectable
for Purity and safety their fish oil is
pure potent and sustainably sourced
another major benefit is that you won't
find any fillers in their fish soil see
the dirty secret in the industry here is
that most companies will add non EPA and
dhas to their fish oil to keep their
quote fish oil count high but to keep
the active ingredients and therefore
costs low it makes you actually feel
like when you're purchasing it you're
getting more fish oil at a cheaper price
but you actually have to double or
triple your dose to get the same amount
of active ingredient which means you end
up spending more money in the long run
or you don't and you get worse results
if you want to give their fish oil a
shot or any other momentous product go
to live mous.com perform to get 20% off
your order again that's live mous.com
perform to get 20% off today's episode
is also brought To Us by David David
makes protein bars unlike anything I've
ever encountered they have an amazing 28
g of protein only 150 calories and z g
of sugar that's right 28 g of protein
and 75% of its calories come from
protein this is 50% higher than the next
closest protein bar honestly it's the
best tasting protein bar I've ever had
in my life by a mile now I don't usually
talk about products before their launch
but These Bars by David represent a
meaningful breakthrough in both
macronutrients and taste and when you
guys try it you will know what I mean
after lots of research and development
these David proin bars are releasing to
the public in September of
2024 the macronutrients one more time
are 28 g of protein 150 calories and 0o
gram of sugar and they do this with
excellent ingredients if you're
interested in trying these bars for
yourself you can go to
david.com perform to purchase if
possible or be notified when they're
available again that's David protein.com
perform to purchase if possible or be
notified when they are available so to
this point we really been dancing around
this idea of what lactate is and I've
been trying to argue that it's been
misunderstood and so now at this point I
think you're convinced and so it's time
for me to actually explain to you what
it really is and how it's working to get
us going the very first thing we need to
address is the name you've heard me
continuously refer to it as lactate now
and not lactic acid lactic acid is
almost never existed in the human body
see what the functional difference is
this when you make a lactate molecule in
human physiology at our temperature and
pH it almost immediately disassociates
into what's called a lactide anion so
this is actually written as a capital l
little a negative and that means it has
a negative charge so it's a lactide
anion with a hydrogen plus ion so one
thing you really got to keep in mind
physiology in in fact chemistry in
general
biochemistry will regulate charges I
mean by that is a positive and a
negative charge um dramatically in fact
this is how all of chemistry works works
right it's positive and negative Charges
going back and forth and this is what
determines how all molecules function
and so you don't ever want a a situation
in your body in which something is
floating around with a positive or
negative charge you almost always want
to combine it so that they are
neutralized and this is why when you
take various um supplements that they
have weird things attached to them
citric acid is a very common one um
salts a common one so they can balance
charges so that they actually get into
your system they don't get immediately
broken down or metabolized or connected
with something else you want so positive
and neutral charges are are absolutely
essential to understanding what's going
on here and so you're never really going
to see lactic acid in that form because
it would require that hydrogen to be
placed on top of it and it's going to
immediately
dissociate keep this in mind later as
this is going to tell you the entire
story of what we're going to talk about
hydrogen itself is a H+ that is almost
synonymous with proton so remember
protons electrons negative charges
positive charges right so if you have a
free floating hydrogen anywhere that is
going to be synonymous with acid in fact
the term pH right so if you have a low
PH you're acidic a high pH is alkaline
so a lot of acid going around pH
depending on who you want to pick stands
for either potential hydrogen or power
of hydrogen but the point is pH is
simply a measure of how much free
hydrogen is around more free hydrogen
more acid that it's the same thing so
that H+ is acid so anytime walking you
through this this biochemistry here and
you hear me say things like this results
in a free hydrogen I might say a free
hydrogen I might say proton I might say
acid in your brain you can hear that all
is the same thing right there's no other
sources of acid than hydrogen so the
opposite of pH is O negative and so an
acid is a lot of H alkaline is a lot of
O Negative you bring those together you
take a acid you take a base you put them
together and you make water that's how
the whole system works great now lactate
itself can come in two basic forms L
lactate and D lactate in humans we're
almost always talking about L lactate
when we think about D we're typically
thinking about the food industry so
you're talking about sauerkraut and
pickles and yogurt um sour milk like we
talked about earlier beer Tomatoes uh
apples wine etc etc almost all those
have a combination of D and L lactate
but they're functionally a little bit
different Recent research is actually
coming out on the role of deact in
humans and particularly regarding the
gut microbiome and so you can actually
see you probably noticed something
there's this connection here between
fermentation fermentable Foods
sauerkraut yogurts gut microbiome health
and there is a strong relationship there
in fact one of the things that's
possibly probably potentially happening
is when we ingest more fiber we know
that this is generally good for gut
microbiome Health but potentially and
this is a strong potential again the
research is very recent here and there's
a ton to learn about the gut microbiome
but that is aiding in the ability to
ferment that fiber that is then
producing high quality results like
lactate and so one particular thought
that's being espoused right now by Dr
books and others is that maybe deact is
a byproduct of some of the bacteria in
your gut
microbiome is increasing the amount of
lactate in your
system which is a good thing
I told you go back to the beginning
remember all the positive things lactate
is associated with and so this could be
one of the many reasons why a healthy
gut microbiome is important for overall
health and
performance again very early but very
interesting and the connection seems to
make some sense we also can take a look
at the research uh I know my group um
lead author great giki we actually
published a review article very recently
on the changes in the gut microb with
acute exercise there's a lot going on we
have an additional study going on right
now on the gut microbiome in female
athletes and there seems to be a
pronounced and positive Association
there with the ability to work with
lactate in various forms um there are
changes in athletes uh in the again the
bacteria associated with lactate
production and clearance U and then it
goes the other direction as well so a
lot to learn in this area but there
seems to be a very strong connection
there with the ability to process clear
generate and handle lactate through the
gut microbiome through the blood as well
as in physical activity so in fact
because of all that there's some idea
right now that deact could be an
important biomarker for overall
intestinal permeability more on that
stuff later but an interesting idea
nonetheless so like I said while that
part of the field is growing and
evolving what's extraordinarily clear is
lactates role in regulating metabolic
acidosis yeah that's right not
contributing or causing in regulating it
as in stopping it from happening or even
reversing it now metabolic acidosis is
the increase in acidic level of your
blood in response to metabolism that's
most simply its point but think about it
this way your body regulates a number of
things to keep you alive how much blood
sugar you have your blood pressure to
make sure you're moving blood throughout
your system but over on top of all of
that the single most important thing for
your body to regulate at all times is
your pH level if you become too acidic
or too alkaline all the enzymes in your
body for the most part stop working
you'll die very quickly it's a huge
problem and so making sure you're not
either alkalic or acidotic getting too
far outside those ranges is the single
top priority of your body at all times
and you've got to keep your brain alive
number one and you've got to make sure
your pH is on point and so when you get
to a situation where you are are
slightly acidic and it's not that much
by the way the pH regulation and body is
very tightly controlled uh especially
relative to things even like lactate
concentrations which can go up orders of
magnitude you don't change pH very much
under any circumstances so if you were
to alter your pH um say at a baseline of
somewhere in the neighbor we'll just
make it like 7.1 7.4 pH and you were to
go down to like five you're dead right
so you're going to keep it way way way
tighter than that right getting you
would trust me if you got if your pH was
below six or below seven into the sixes
you would be feeling that um very very
very much so metabolic acidosis that
particular case again as when the pH or
the concentration of acid gets too high
and so just take for example one of the
fastest ways that you could deal with
that is to get an IV of lactate this is
a very common thing in cases of
dehydrations when folks are really
really dehydrated we will use what's
called a ringer solution so this is
typically combination of fluids of
course and then a bunch of salts right
so you're talking sodium chloride sodium
lactate potassium chloride a whole bunch
of electrolytes to balance osmotic
pressure to keep fluids in the system
but really you're getting a ton of
lactate because it can go to the liver
immediately be converted in what's
called bicarbonate and bicarbonate could
then kind of eat up all the free pH all
the free hydrogens rather that are
floating around and now careful
terminology and increase your pH meaning
reduce acid level right higher pH means
more alkaline so don't want to confuse
you there but the point is you give
somebody a bunch of lactate in that form
you're going to make a bunch of
bicarbonate and you're going to reduce
uh you're going to alter what's
happening at the kidney with urine
secretion and you're going to make
yourself more alkaline back to normal so
this is a very any any of you in the
medical field that are listening are
like yeah yeah this is like very basic
medical physiology 101 lactate will help
with metabolic acidosis but if I really
had to boil it down I would say the
three primary roles of lactate in your
body is number one it is the primary
energy source of mitochondrial
respiration two it is the primary
precursor of gluconeogenesis and then
three it is a signaling molecule or
hormone in order to understand this
we've got to talk about metabolism and
learn how you actually produce cellular
energy now in humans you've got two
primary places you can go fats and
carbohydrates and there are some pros
and cons to each and in fact really the
way to think about this is not such as
like a one's better than the other one
that's completely misunderstanding the
point they are meant to be complimentary
they want to give you options this is
what metabolic flexibility means the
ability to use fat or carbohydrates in
the best possible situation this allows
you to be most efficient as well as most
productive create tons of energy when
you need it and not waste any when you
don't but the way in which we create
energy from fats and carbohydrates is
quite different and so from the highest
onset fat has to use aerobic metabolism
keep that in mind there are no ways in
human physiology to anerobic metabolize
fat carbohydrates though are
particularly powerful because it can do
both anerobic and aerobic metab
metabolism what's that mean fun and this
is not totally true but fundamentally I
want you to think about when you hear
the word aerobic associate that with
mitocondria in other words saying we
have to use oxygen and we have to have
the mitochondria in play to go through
aerobic metabolism I don't have to have
that for anerobic oxygen can be around
to do anerobic but it's not required
either and so when you are imagin
yourself as a little muscle cell and you
need to create some energy and you're
deciding what do I use fat or
carbohydrate think about it this way way
the benefit of fat as a fuel source is
it's basically Unlimited in fact most
people even fairly lean people have
enough fat on their body to power 30
plus days of continuous exercise I don't
mean working out every day I mean start
running right now and don't stop for 30
straight days you probably still will
have enough fat Supply on your body to
stay alive it's effectively unlimited
and unending why don't you just use all
fat for fuel then well the problem is
it's way too slow when you use fat as a
fuel source for exercise it comes
effectively from the entire body equally
and so if your hamstring is Contracting
so that you can run you're pulling fat
from your forearm from your hamstring
from your back from your fingers and
anywhere else it's coming from the
entire system which means it has to be
broken down mobilized taken into muscle
tissue muscle tissue then has to bring
it into the mitochondria and then we can
start producing energy the other part
about it is molecule per molecule fat is
less efficient as a fuel source than
carbohydrate and so it's an unending
Supply but it's slow and less efficient
which means it's fantastic for times of
low energy need it's great when I'm
doing what I'm doing right now talking
sitting walking low levels of exercise
it can be used because I have plenty of
time but anytime I need fuel faster or
energy faster I need to switch to
carbohydrate now remember carbohydrates
start anerobic and finish a aerobically
which means I can get going right now
and I can get going and I can be used
during really high intensity exercise
when I don't have enough time to bring
in and utilize oxygen and so again not
fat is not better or worse than
carbohydrate carbohydrate is much faster
you get carbohydrate from a couple of
places most specifically and initially
it's coming from stored carbohydrates in
the actual exercising muscle itself we
call this muscle glycogen if you need it
from somewhere else it's going to come
from your blood we call this blood
glucose if you need extra Supply from
that you can get it from the liver which
stores muscle glycogen it breaks the
glycogen down puts it in the form of
glucose puts that in your blood and then
you can steal it that way and so in fact
one of the classic things that happens
when you initially start exercising is
despite the fact that you are pulling in
glucose into your muscle cells blood
glucose levels rise and that's because
of an anticipatory response the liver
starts kicking a bunch into the blood
because it knows you're going to take it
and you don't want blood glucose levels
to drop because then you're going to
pass out because you don't have glucose
for your brain in fact this is why if
you see somebody like the end of an
endurance race pass out one of the first
things that the EMT staff and stuff will
do is they'll come over and give them
really fast absorbing sugars candies
juices stuff like that to get blood
sugar to come up really fast because I
know blood sugar is very very
low anyways back to the point so
carbohydrates are fantastic because they
are right there and so at this point we
need to think about what is the actual
chemistry of carbohydrates and how does
that relate to lactate and actually
really more importantly why is that than
helpful to the brain to the heart to the
liver to wound healing and all the other
stuff we talked about earlier and then
of course why is this actually helping
me perform one of the things you're
going to hear me talk about a little bit
later is there's a strong association
between better athletic performance when
you can produce more lactate and that's
because of what I said at the very
beginning here remember it is a potent
fuel it is a strong signal send the
ability to go to your liver to make more
glucose and it is a hormone it is a
signal um it has many functions there
and in fact more recent papers describe
it as that lacto hormone which is a fun
way of saying it can communicate with
other cells in order to be called a
hormone what this actually functionally
means is one cell has the ability to
communicate to another one and so what
we'll say for lactate is it has both
autocrine paracrine and endocrine um
characteristics so autocrine meaning it
can signal its own cell to do things
paracrine meaning it can go to
neighboring cells so you're talking
other muscle fibers within the same
exercising muscle or it can actually
have an endocrine function which means
it can get in the blood and go to any
other tissue you're going to see this
later because it's going to get in the
blood and it's going to go to other
muscle it's going to go to the liver
it's going to go to the kidneys it's
going to go to the brain it's going to
go to the heart and a bunch of other
plac it's going to go to the digestive
tract and it's going to provide them
with important signals um as well as be
used as a direct fuel source okay so now
going back uh to where we're at with
overall metabolism when we said it has
those three powerful UH responsibilities
I quickly talked about it that third one
right that's what I mean when I say it's
a signaling molecule or mechanism or
hormone the one above that when I said
it is the primary precursor for
gluconeogenesis lactate can go into the
blood get sent then back back to your
liver and even kidney and go through
What's called the Corey cycle in this we
can actually take lactate combine it
together and make glucose so the way
that I call this is it is a precursor to
glucon neogenesis gluco meaning glucose
Neo meaning new genesis meaning create
so how you can create new glucose
molecules out of non-glucose and so
again all we really have to do and I'll
explain this in a second is take two
lactate molecules smoos them together
and I've made myself glucose and so
that's an important rule um as it's in
in the precursor of
gluconeogenesis the third one was it's
being the primary fuel source for
mitochondrial
respiration now again I apologize I know
I'm throwing lots of different terms
around if you are in chemistry instead
of saying monoch condal respiration you
probably say aerobic metabolism they're
not exactly interchangeable as I've
discussed earlier fermentation is not
the same as anerobic glycolysis again
functional distinction there when you're
talking about bacteria or food types of
things we're going to call it
fermentation when you're talking about
in exercising muscle itself it's now
anerobic glycolosis coming from
mitochondria and so again trying to not
throw you off in terminology but as
you're reading or hearing other things
that's really what we're talking about
and so the ability um of lactate to be a
primary fuel for mitochondri
respiration is exactly how we started
the show one of the primary things that
lactate does is stimulate mitochondrial
biogenesis it tells your body to make
more and make bigger mitochondria and in
fact it works together in this entire
meshing network when we generally talk
about mitochondria people kind of think
about it as these independent units but
more recent research is suggesting that
is really truly a network effect you're
probably familiar with mitochondria but
is incredibly important for exercise
performance and a number of overall
Health and Longevity metrics and so
people go out of their weight to try to
stimulate and increase and uh have
various protocols that they do to to
enhance
mitochondria and lactate is probably the
best one and so that right there is
explaining why you should be paying
attention to it if you care about
mitochondria it's the top place to go to
increase it or improve its quality so to
get get back to the biochemistry what's
happening here remember fat as a fuel is
coming from the entire body carbohydrate
it's coming from the cell that is
exercising itself fat has to go through
aerobic metabolism which means it has to
go into mitochondria but
carbohydrates are going to start
anerobic
and finish aerobically or finish in the
mitochondria so as a very quick reminder
your muscle cells have two functionally
different areas they've got What's
called the cytoplasm or cytool which is
kind of like this jelly filled thing
that's all around the inside of your
cells all your organel are inside of
that and then in this particular case
you've got
mitochondria anerobic metabolism whether
we're talking about creatine or in this
case carbohydrate happens in that cytool
if you want to then use aerobic
metabolism We've Got to Now shift into
the mitochondria and this is another
reason why aerobic energy from either
carbohydrates or fat just takes a little
bit longer because we have to have that
even even when we're in the muscle cell
there's that additional step needed to
get it into mitochondria to then really
go through the metabolic processes there
all right now last little back backgound
before we really get into this
story remember fat and carbohydrates are
just functionally large chains of carbon
so a fat is the case of a triglyceride
is a glyceride which is a carbohydrate
it is a glyceride three carbon molecule
each one of those carbons has a long
chain of carbons attached to it that we
call a fatty acid so a tri glyceride is
Three fatty acids attached to a glycerol
backbone think of it this way it is a
three carbon
carbohydrate with three long chains of
fatty acids and all those long chains of
fatty acids are carbons depending on how
many carbons are there we call it a
different fatty acid steric acid or
lenic acid or other things like that if
they're perfectly bonded we call it
saturated if it's has one missing Bond
or two missing bonds we call it
unsaturated polyunsaturated Etc but
we're talking big long chains of carbon
so when one molecule of fat comes in to
a cell for energy we have a lot of Po
IAL
carbons however
carbohydrates in the case of exercise
remember it's coming from
glucose that is a six carbon chain so it
is much smaller so benefit of fat on
ending and way more
carbon per molecule carbohydrate way
faster can go anerobic in the muscle but
only six total carbons why this
functionally matters here is all of
metabolism summed up in about 5 Seconds
you break off carbon you run it through
a whole bunch of steps and processes to
get rid of that that releases energy you
use that energy to make a molecule
called ATP you then get rid of carbon
put it in your blood put it in your
lungs and breathe it out so you breathe
in
oxygen you break up fat or
carbohydrates by breaking those carbon
chains you give off energy use that
energy to make ATP the waste product is
carbon you attach that to the oxygen to
make carbon dioxide you breathe that out
so the net result of all metabolism is
three things and three things only
ATP water and carbon
dioxide now if you were in my laboratory
I could put a little mask on you connect
you to what's called a metabolic chamber
and I could actually identify how much
fat you're using for fuel or
carbohydrates you're using for fuel a
little bit of math that goes on there we
can figure that out because of the
different efficiencies between car
hydrate and fat like I said earlier but
the point is by simply measuring carbon
dioxide I can measure and identify what
you're burning for your fuel and one of
the things that tells us when you start
increasing lactate and you pass into
these different areas of aerobic or
anerobic metabolism is when the rate of
carbon dioxide that you're making or
exhaling starts to now be different than
your rate of breathing and I can now
tell okay wait a minute those things
should be in lock step step but when
they're not the rate of increase of
carbon dioxide is different than the
rate of ventilation I know you've
switched ways you're getting energy
that's the quick version of what's
happening there right now while you are
doing low levels of exercise or even all
the way down to sleep it is advantageous
for you to use fat as a fuel source
again Unlimited Supply I don't have to
run it out I have a limited supply of
carbohydrates I can only store so much
in muscle very very small amount
typically like a couple of teaspoons
total of glucose in my blood and then
very small amounts in my liver remember
the liver is like the football size
thing relative to how much fat you could
potentially have on your body that's
unlimited and so carbohydrates are
always meant to sort of be there for
sustained living and high powerered
exercise and fat is your backup tank
it's your reserve right now when I start
going through exercise the ideal
situation would be to spare my glycogen
spare my glucose spare my car
carbohydrates okay all same thing here
so now ideally you would use all fat for
fuel that keep you nice and lean of
course and we wouldn't be wasting our
preserves and our concentrations of
carbohydrate but because it's slow what
effectively happens is at rest we have a
value that's called rer or RQ so this is
stands for Respiratory exchange ratio or
respiratory quot typically
78 something like that in a a lot of
people maybe a little bit lower if
you're fit and that suggests that you're
burning mostly carbohydrates but a
decent percentage of fat as you
increased exercise intensity that number
will climb in fact a score of
1.0 literally means that you're burning
100%
carbohydrate because I can't break down
and utilize fat as a fuel source
anerobic as soon as I cross that aerobic
into anerobic space of exercise I now
cross out of my ability to use fat as a
fuel another way to say that once
exercise intensity gets too high I can't
use fat as a fuel and so from there I'm
lowering the percentage of energy that's
coming from fat and increasing the
percentage of energy that's coming from
carbohydrates such that when I get to
truly high-intensity exercise that
number becomes 100 and zero all my
energy from carbs none of it from fat
the opposite never exists you can never
be in a situation where you're burning
100% fat in fact the highest you're
going to probably get maybe 60% fat
maybe
70% not much higher than that though
maybe you could argue me 75 but that'd
be sort of your Peak and so we are
uniquely positioned as humans and all
mammals really to burn carbohydrates
that is the primary fuel source by a
landslide basic physiology will tell us
that doesn't mean we only want to use it
in fact the idea of metabolic
flexibility is I have strong capacity to
go back and forth between utilizing fat
and utilizing carbohydrates now a lot of
folks u in the last couple of years have
significantly misinterpreted and
misdescribed what metabolic flexibility
is perhaps we'll do an entire show on
that maybe we should how to test it
identify it improve it etc etc but
metabolic flexibility does not stand for
your ability to maximize fat burning
that is not at all what it is it is
exactly what I just said the ability to
use both effectively if you hedge
towards only fat burning or hedge
towards only carbohydrate burning those
are not metabolically flexible you want
to do both more on that later perhaps if
you all are interested so as I get to
this high intensity of exercise in fact
this is one of the ways um one of our
metrics we use to identify whether or
not you're at a V2 Max is do you cross a
threshold of 1.1 on your re is the
typical standard there which
mathematicians are saying well wait a
minute I thought 1.0 is 100 and it is
and so anything above that actually
represents you
hyperventilating which again tells us
kind of where you're at so I've actually
seen um I'm myself pretty typically can
get to like 1.35 1.4 I've seen plenty of
athletes get up there um which means you
are producing a significant amount of
carbon dioxide as a waste product and
you are in significant discomfort as
well and so that's really what's
happening right we're burning a lot of
carbohydrates at high intensity um and
the lower the intensity goes the lower
um the more fat we're burning as a fuel
why is that well this is exactly based
on story geometry and chemistry of how
we can get to energy so when we make
when we use fat as a fuel source let's
say we broke it down from our back of
our arm or our face or whatever and we
want to use it to power energy in our
hamstring the fat has to get put into
blood it's got to get transported on a
protein it's got to get into our
exercising muscle it's got to go through
Transporters there it's got to then get
transported into mitochondria that is
limited by the amount of carnitine
that's there some of you may have
explored and use carnitine as a
supplement that's exactly why that's the
rate limiting step okay now the more
mitochondria I have the more then I can
bring in and the more carnitine I have
on the mo on the mitochondria themselves
the more I can bring in but I have to
bring that in the problem is you have
these giant long chains six 18 carbons
they're too big they can't get into the
mitochondria so what you do is you cut
off two at a time and I know exercise
physiologists I know biochemists I'm
skipping a tremendous number of steps
here but nonetheless you're going to cut
off two carbons at a time this matters
this matters to lactate hang one second
and I'll tell you why when you cut off
those two carbons at a time that is
called beta oxidation you've used oxygen
to do that and it's beta because you cut
off one two of the carbons those two
carbons can then get transported into
the
mitochondria those two carbons together
like that are called acetal
COA very important acetal COA that goes
into the mitochondria can run through a
thing called KB cycle by doing that you
use these high intermediate exchanges
with things like NAD which will come
back to an fad you use that to shuttle
protons hydrogen pluses and electrons
around you send them to a thing called
the electron transport chain all that is
used to then create a bunch of ATP as a
byproduct of that you burn off one two
carbons and so you had a two carbon
molecule go into the KB cycle it comes
out as carbon dioxide ATP and water
remember earlier final product of allall
metabolism is those three molecules so
now we have taken a carbo a fat rather
taken it into our mitochondria and run
all the carbons out I just continue to
cut off two at a time two at a time two
at a time until that entire fatty acid
chain is
metabolized highly effective
process but slow limited by my ability
to bring in oxygen get that oxygen into
blood get that oxygen from the blood
into my exercising tissue get that into
mitochondria now in other episode we
talked about V2 Max I believe that's in
the cardiac or the heart episode I went
through all of those things avo2
difference and limiting factors the
central factors to Performance so you
can see that episode for more there but
that's effectively the problem right we
thought for many years lactate was
produced because of an insufficiency of
oxygen in that mitochondria in other
words it's limited by that we now know
that's totally wrong in fact the
evidence is not only clear it is uh
Beyond reproach fuel through your muscle
is never Limited by oxygen that's never
going to be the limiting step for
lactate specifically so lactate is
created not because we're out of oxygen
but for some other reasons so that's the
quick story of fat
metabolism understanding that let's
transfer back over to figure out how
these carbohydrates are broken down
doesn't really matter for this story if
we're starting with muscle glycogen if
we're getting the glucose from the blood
or if we're getting glucose that was
glycogen in the liver put into blood and
now broken in either way
let's just stay with the place of
glycogen in the muscle it's right there
you start going for exercise I don't
have to worry about mobilizing the fat
and bringing in it I don't have to wait
for oxygen to come in I can get bringing
in energy right now and so in this
particular case carbohydrate the
chemical formula is C6
h126 what's that mean why does that
matter that is six
carbons attached to six H2O molecules
folks that's what carbohydrate
means it is a carbon that has been
hydrated it is one carbon and one water
in the case of glucose there are six of
them now if you go to fructose or some
other forms of sugar or carbohydrate
they have different amounts of carbon
but in this particular case you have six
carbons attached to six Waters that is a
carbohydrate so when that is inside the
muscle cell the cytoplasm if you will
sitting there and we've decided to not
use phosphor as a fuel source which is
the primary and fastest one and we want
to use carbohydrates this initial step
is what we call anerobic
glycolysis again if you take that and
put that into a bacteria you'd call that
fermentation in your muscle we call it
anerobic glycolysis lysis means to split
or to break and gly meaning the glycogen
or glucose so we're splitting and
breaking this thing apart we're doing it
without the use of oxygen and so it is
anerobic and so if you can visualize
this any of you watching this you've got
six carbons that are all chained
together now instead of breaking two off
like we did in the case of beta
oxidation and fat we split the entire
molecule in half so we have two separate
three carbon
molecules we call that pyruvate so we
have not lost any carbon in this
exchange but we have broken a chemical
bond this is given off some energy this
itself gives us two ATP give you a
little bit of an example if we go back
to earlier when we take acetyl COA and
take it through the C R cycle and you
get 25 or 28 ATP in this particular
process we make two so energy amount
that we create from this process of
anerobic glym is very low but it's not
bad either okay we have actually made it
with a little bit less oxygen and we
made it really fast because we didn't
have to
wait here's the
downside this process as many of the
processes as we'll see later is limited
by this molecule called
NAD your ability to go through all the
Met
olism is determined by your ability to
regulate
PH meaning enzymes don't work in highly
acidic or highly alkaline environments
you won't let things go through if you
can't balance positive and negative
charges so what you do with naad is you
shuttle hydrogens back and forth through
molecules doesn't depending on what's
Happening it could be going different
ways but you're going to go from a
molecule called NAD to a thing called
nadh hydrogen
and an
H+ if you want to go the other direction
you ship it back and so you were limited
a large part by how much NAD you have
because as soon as you run out of NAD
you can't run these processes because
you won't be able to handle all the
hydrogens that are built up critical
step in fact um in a second here this
may me think of something else I'll
explain to you why that helps you with
hangovers really soon okay so that
that's our our process so by doing that
we split these this like or this glucose
into two separate molecules called
pyruvate and by doing that we've
shuttled a couple of NAD nadh's across
each other and made a couple of ATP and
that's all well and
dandy the perate itself is fine back to
Anor robic threshold back to how I was
taught in exercise physiology what we
initially thought was this is the end of
anerobic glycolysis we're done at
pyruvate if we had oxygen we would then
take the pyruvate break off one carbon
each so the three carbon molecule pyate
you cut off one carbon you make it a two
carbon molecule and that's acetal COA
that's gone into the mitochondria and it
runs the exact same KB cycle or tricylic
acid cycle as I described earlier with
fat identical literally the same thing
it is the exact same precursor it's the
exact same substrate exact same process
exact same amount of ATP created
identical okay like I said carbohydrates
start anerobic and always finish
aerobically identical to Fat at this
point if we run out of oxygen or don't
have enough oxygen that pyate is then
converted into lactate okay that was the
original and that's how I was taught we
now know that the end product of that
pyate is always lactate and we know this
from a lot of different areas of
research um the the
concentration you typically have
something like 10 to 50 to one amount of
lactate that you do py so it's almost
never there which tells you lactate is
very quickly being created out of
pyruvate as soon as pyu is being created
um that number can go up in order of a
magnitude during exercise and so it
doesn't make any sense to think that
that you're stopping at pyu furthermore
there has been an excellent research
identifying Transporters specific to
both pyruvate and lactate that get you
into the mitochondria and so some
pyruvate can be moved in mitochondria
and a lot of lactate can as well we also
know that those m CT uh is the the
abbreviation for those Transporters or
in a number of different cells
throughout your body uh and so we can
move it throughout and that's one of the
reasons why we have this lactate shuttle
um ability so here's what we think at
this understanding right now and of
course as research comes on board we
learn more things we might change our
opinion but according to the research
right now the prevailing thought is the
end product of anerobic metabolism is
always lactate the majority of that is
going to go into the mitochondria in the
working cell some portion of it is going
to leave muscle in fact what happens
here is once your ability to process
that lactate is
exceeded by your lactate production in
other words you're making more lactate
than you can handle in that cell you
begin to transport the lactate out of
the cell we call that lactate efux you
put it into the bloodstream and you ship
it to a number of different areas the
first place you ship it to are neighor
neighboring muscle fibers that are not
working or have a greater ability to
process lactate now think about it this
way anerobic metabolism is more common
in your fast twitch fibers aerobic
metabolism is more common in slow twitch
fibers the amount of an enzyme called
lactate dehydrogenase which is the
enzyme that switches you back and forth
between lactate and pyruvate is about
50% higher in slow twitch fibers and so
we're creating it in fast twitch fibers
and likely shipping it into slow twitch
fibers so those slow twitch fibers got a
pre-digested half broken down sugar
molecule it's an insanely effective fuel
source it didn't have to do anything
didn't have to increase its acid
concentration didn't have to run through
any of its NAD and I got a pre-digested
if you will fuel source at the same time
the the fastro fiber benefits from being
able to run through metabolism faster
and not having to deal with the waste
products so it's a win-win win win win
if those muscles don't want it it can go
again as I said earlier in the blood and
can go to the kidney or liver for the
gluconeogenesis it can go to the heart
which absolutely loves lactate as a fuel
source in fact the heart is the biggest
consumer of lactate of any organ in the
body it's actually the preferred fuel
source over glucose especially during a
schic or anytime oxygen concentrations
get low in the heart it loves it it can
go to the brain and the astrocytes
actually which are like these star like
neurons that are all or cells that are
all across the central nervous system
they prefer lactate as a fuel over
glucose or anything else in fact this is
also why um you see things like ketones
and other noncarbohydrate fuel sources
because we know we need that as fuel for
asites and lactate is basically again
pre-digested carbohydrate so it is
adored across the entire physiological
system as a lovely fuel source so not
only is it grabbing on and holding on
and making you less acidic is a phen
phal signaling mechanism as well as a
direct fuel source for almost every
tissue in your body I'd like to take a
quick break and thank our sponsors
today's episode is brought to you by ag1
ag1 is a foundational nutrition greens
supplement that means ag1 provides a
variety of vitamins minerals probiotics
prebiotics and adaptogens in an easy to
drink greens powder initially I was very
skeptical of ag1 as I am with all
supplement companies frankly but after
months of discussions with their lead
nutrition scientists and the team at ag1
I've been impressed by their commitment
to sourcing the highest quality
ingredients and rigorous testing to
ensure that every single batch is free
of banned substances allergens heavy
metals microbes pesticides herbicides
residual solvents and microt toxins it's
even earned the prestigious NSF
certified for sport third-party testing
approval now ag1 is not a replacement
for eating Whole Foods but it is a great
way to fill in the gaps and it's been a
big help pushing some of my clients just
in the right direction for eating more
high quality foods because it helps them
with Cravings digestion and many other
benefits now not everyone needs to
consume greens powders but if you're
going to do so you better make sure it
actually includes the ingredients that
it claims to and that those ingredients
are of the best sourcing if you'd like
to try ag1 you can go to drink a1.com
perform to receive five free travel
packs plus a year supply of vitamin D3
plus K2 again that's drink a1.com
perform to receive five free travel
packs plus a year supply of vitamin D3
plus K2 today's episode is also brought
to you by Renaissance periodization if
you want to put on muscle through
science-backed training programs look no
further than Renaissance periodization
RP as we call it in the industry guides
users through effective and easy to
follow lifting programs all through
their hypertrophy app these programs are
designed by the absolute best in the
industry including one of my absolute
favorite sports scientist and
professional bodybuilder Dr Mike isotel
you may recognize that name because I've
referenced him and his work countless
times over the years so whether you're
looking to put on muscle gain strength
or both these programs will help you
achieve your goals and have produced
results in literally thousands of men
and women Renaissance periodization also
has a diet app that is backed by the
latest science and innovation in the
fields of nutrition and takes the
complexity out of dieting helping you
achieve your ideal body composition if
you'd like to try Renaissance
periodization go to rpstrength tocom
perform to save up to $50 off of your
subscription again that's rpst
strength.com perform to save up to $50
off your subscription okay at this point
we've covered how lactate is created and
what it's doing and the different roles
it's having in our body I want to move
on to some other things but before I do
that I got to go back to the promise I
made earlier which is talking about
alcohol now if you pay attention to beer
or wine or spirits of any kind you
probably are recognizing fermentation
and so if I were to take barley or Hops
and introduce some yeast or bacteria to
them and ferment them if I did that long
enough I would create ethanol well
that's basically what I just described
to you in your muscle anyways it's a
very similar process in fact there's a
high exchange here remember earlier when
I was talking about the gut microbiome
being able to create all kinds of
awesome stuff with lactate um PR met
fiber and stuff like that your body
actually is thought to produce around 3
gram or so a day of your own ethanol
through that exact same process it takes
the carbohydrates does the same thing
that that your favorite producers do
when they make your beer or your bourbon
or whatever the case is and your gut
just does the exact same thing however
you're able to clear it really fast so
don't worry no one can smell the ethanol
in your breast because your gut
microbiome um babies do the same thing
by the way it's happening in fetuses and
all that stuff so it's it's a normal
part of all physiology and so there is
this very strong tie between these
things now what you can actually do is
is kind of go in reverse and so
ethanol typically is associated with
even things like methane um this is
associated with fermentation and foul
smelling gases in fact if that process
is happening too much in your stomach
then you can have some pretty
significant GI distress and this is one
of the reasons why carbohydrates are the
primary cause of uh flatulence and
overall gas but nonetheless what's
really happening is you you've got your
ethanol alcohol you've created it
yourself or you've brought it in that's
ethanol um etto if you're in my lab
you'll see all the bottles with e on
them that stands for ethanol we use that
to clean surfaces and a bunch of
different things in our action but if
you were to have this in the form of an
alcoholic drink or whatever um your body
would bring this in and it runs almost
identical to the pyu metabolism that I
just talked about so you can take
ethanol and the very first thing you're
going to do is is convert that into a
thing called acetal now that is highly
toxic and primarily responsible for
hangovers and so one of the things
that's happening is when you bring in
that ethanol again you're immediately
digesting it as quickly as you can in
your liver when you do that because it
has to go through the liver for the most
part because this is metabolism now you
can think about that this as basic
carbohydrate metabolism now when you
increase carbohydrate metabolism you
tend to decrease fat metabolism and the
opposite right so these are kind of
working back and forth so unlike earlier
when we talked about the lactate shuttle
and I said hey you should stop thinking
about lactate um as this this negative
byproduct you also need to really stop
thinking about aerobic and anerobic
Metabolism as a tug-of-war it's not good
or bad it is more like a chain on a
bicycle so that's that the chain is the
lactate and turning of one gear turns
the other one this is a fundamental
rethinking of how we understand
metabolism and energy production
anerobic and aerobic metabolism are not
at each other's throats they are
productive and lactate is the signaling
mechanism from one to the other one it
is the precursor for mitochondrial
biogenesis it is a precursor for
gluconeogenesis it is the signaling
mechanism it is this this as George
Brooks called it in one of his more
recent papers it is the Phoenix Rising
again it is a restored understanding
that this is a collective Cooperative
relationship between aerobic and
anerobic it is not a tug-of-war that is
the absolutely wrong way to think about
it so when we're in the liver here and
we're handling this carbohydrate
metabolism because the need to go
through carbohydrate and anerobic
glycolysis is so high it shuts down fat
utilization why this is problematic is
this is why high amounts of alcohol
consumption is associated with fatty
acid development in the liver this
exactly what happens you're supposed to
be metabolizing the fat there but you
can't because you're too busy processing
the alcohol and so that fat then becomes
stored you shifted the burden it's also
why um alcohol intake is associated with
overall fat storage because again you're
downregulating fat storage everywhere
because you're upregulating the need to
do the ethanol in your liver that fat
then gets stored everywhere else now as
long as your calories are equated it's a
little bit different but alcohol
typically comes in chloric excess and so
then you got extra calories that need to
be burned but you can't burn fat so they
get stored so that ethanol then like I
said is is supposed to be converted into
um acetal alide acetal alahh is very
easy to then convert into acetate which
is then converted directly into acetyl
COA
so you're right back to where you
started the ability to cruise back and
forth between pyruvate acetal alahh and
all the way up to ethanol is fairly
quick to be totally honest with you and
so you can Cruise back and forth between
those things and so whether um you're a
bacteria or in your own um system you're
whether you're creating yourself you can
create some um some acetate yourself you
can go backwards up and down that chain
but really you're you're talking one
step away and so ethanol again acetal
aldhy tons of that going through
metabolism that concentration gets
really high you get super hung over so
what do you do about
it well this is one of the reasons why
getting a big sweat in the next day or
going for a run or working out tends to
help some of the symptoms not all of
them there are many symptoms associated
with The Hangover but one of the things
that you're doing is you're increasing
the demand for acetal koay doesn't
matter if you're going aerobic or
anerobic because remember acetyl KOA
comes from the breakdown of fat or
carbohydrates anerobic or aerobically
it's going to get there and so you've
increased your demand for acetyl COA so
instead of leaving things in the form of
acetyl alahh which again is really
problematic you force it to converted
into aceto Quay because you've increased
the demand for that and so you can kind
of think of it as like the old College
you know I man I got to go burn out all
the alcohol uh to get out of my system
that's not exactly what's happening but
it's also not super far off either
you're really just using it as a fuel
source now alcohol as a fuel source for
exercise performance is not a good thing
this is a very very slow and rate
limited process in fact this is being
limited heavily by NAD concentrations
you're going to run out of them and so
that process gets backed up very very
very quickly um you can do a handful of
things to potentially uh try to escalate
that or keep that going faster but the
reality of it is your liver is only so
big it can certainly take a beating um
it is one of the most regenerative
tissues in all the body but that said
you're going to only
metabolize um alcohol so in fact some of
you have probably heard of some people
metabolize alcohol much faster than
others and that's specifically because
the acetyl alide dehydrogenase molecule
the more that you have the faster you
metabolize alcohol the slower the lower
this is this is the red face flush and
all those other things associated with
low alcohol metabolism so alcohol
metabolism fermentation anerobic
exercise carbohydrate starches all this
stuff very very similar fermented foods
all this stuff can really come back to
in some part lactate okay so to get us
back on track here up to this point
we've talked about what lactate really
is and its role in physiology and then
more specifically exercise
physiology but if you're a curious mind
you may be thinking to yourself a
handful of things wait a
minute so I'm confused at this point is
more lactate good or bad you keep saying
it's good Andy but I haven't quite made
that connection and if so how is it
really good what is it doing maybe go a
step further if it's good is more better
and what is mean more in the cell more
getting out of the cell more in blood
what really is going on here and so can
you really just can you Andy can you
bring it all together for me and help me
truly understand the role of lactate
what it's doing for my body and why it's
positively affecting all these other
organs outside of exercising muscle
let's start off by just answering the
question of well is more lactate
better that's a little bit tricky to
answer so remember lactate is created in
exercising muscle and then at some point
when that rate of production exceeds how
much the mondri can handle it starts
getting pushed into blood now in order
for me to know how much lactate is
actually going on in your muscle I'd
have to go in and take a biopsy so
that's really tricky the easier way to
understand that is to measure it in
Blood and so we can look at things like
onset of blood lactate concentrations
how much lactates in your plasma or
whole blood overall and different things
like that and kind of depending on which
metric you look at you're going to get
different values different terminology
and so again admittedly that stuff can
to be a little bit tricky I want to try
to simplify it as much as I can for you
right now give you just the overview of
what I think the field is saying rather
than all those individual details
because it will get unnecessarily tricky
at this point well there's research
suggesting that higher level athletes
those that have greater performance in
endurance based events actually are able
to handle more lactate at the same time
there are plenty of anecdotes for folks
like Michael Phelps who supposedly
sustained extremely low concentrations
of lactate I guess this really
highlights a couple things one we don't
really fully understand exercise
biochemistry yet there's clearly some
gaps in our understanding of what's
really happening the second thing is
that we probably have multiple Avenues
to physical success you can imagine some
individuals doing well because they can
handle a lot more lactate others maybe
doing particularly because they don't
produce that much and so they don't have
to deal with that I think it's pretty
clear both of those Avenues are
potential for success again particularly
in endurance events at the same time
look at the research on lactate
supplementation now we know very
effectively that sodium bicarbonate and
other forms of
supplementation that reduce acid buildup
in tissue are quite effective this comes
in a number of varieties so you can take
a look at things like beta alanine
supplementation this increases carnosine
concentrations in muscle tissue and
effectively acts as an acid buffer so it
keeps it lower and so your muscular
endurance and um whether shortterm or
even moderate term exercise events tends
to increase and it's not perfect but
there's a lot of research behind that
similarly you have things like sodium
bicarbonate this is a different
mechanism but same idea and you're
bringing it in bicarbonate as I talked
about earlier it's able to then absorb
some of the free floating hydrogen
protons which Rings your muscle ph up
right less acidic more alkaline so then
when you start producing excess hydrogen
ions from exercise you're at a higher
set point and so then again the pH or
acidinduced fatigue is slow down again a
lot of research on that the problem with
sodium bicarbonate is sometimes can
create GI distress and some other issues
and so a way around that is a handful of
different lotions or creams momentus for
for example makes a thing called PR
lotion which is a sodium bicarbonate
thing that you can apply directly on
muscle uh to again have the same effects
of that lots of different ways around it
momentus is one product but there's
plenty of other ones on the market as
well and so we know that works but what
about then if you just take lactate we
know lactate is another potential
buffering mechanism we know what it can
do it can hold on to those hydrogen
protons for us help with NAD
recirculation etc etc so will this allow
me to continue to go through glycolysis
since I continue to feed back NAD to
that system which we know requires it to
proceed well it's one of those
disappointing aspects of science it
should work makes all the sense in the
world but it doesn't look like it does
the evidence that's available today
suggests minimal or no effect really of
lactate supplements on exercise
performance so if that's what you're
looking for I would encourage you going
through either the sodium bicarbonate
either the powder supplementation pill
or the lotion or something like a beta
alanine um to buffer and improve
performance at the same time there is
much more room for Hope in application
of lactate supplements for other
outcomes in fact I know of multiple
trials led by the legendary George
Brooks who I've mentioned multiple times
georgean as I mentioned is still active
in this field actually he took on one of
my master students Jose aralo a number
of years ago who should be finishing his
PhD up there but they've done a numerous
trials looking at applications of
lactate immediately after traumatic
brain injuries concussions and other
treatments so there's a lot of things to
be excited about about lactate but from
an exercise performance perspective
where we focus most of our time in this
show doesn't really seem to be super
effective that said there's not a
tremendous amount of research probably
more is needed or warranted so if more
comes on board and we get a different
answer I'll be sure to update you when
that time comes I'd like to take a quick
break and thank our sponsors today's
episode is brought to you by continuum
Continuum is a membership only wellness
club designed to help high performers
reach their Fitness and performance
goals Continuum just opened its Flagship
Club in Manhattan quickly making it one
of the most sought-after memberships in
the city its location in Greenwich
Village is incredible in fact it's
stunning it's a 25,000 ft space with
state-of-the-art equipment a beautiful
design and everything you could possibly
want in this unique mix of a gym
Wellness Center and Social Club
Continuum members start with a thorough
Olympic grade assessment that results in
a biometrically driven AI assisted
wellness program that updates in real
time and incorporates everything from
personal training and physical therapy
to Hyperbaric and IV therapies by
bringing together true Fitness Experts
best-in-class technology and proven
Wellness services and amenities
Continuum delivers the most
comprehensive solution to Performance
I've been involved with Continuum
working as their head of performance
science since their founding and I've
been incredibly impressed by what the
team there has built if you're
interested in joining Continuum their
team has agreed to give a select number
of you the listeners here a fully waved
onboarding which includes V2 max testing
dexa scans blood panels sleep analysis
and more all at their Fabulous New York
City Flagship location to learn more
visit continuum. club/ perform again
that's Continuum with two 's. club/
perform I realize at this point now I've
talked about Lac date and conven you
that it's not a cause of muscle fatigue
but I haven't explained to you what is
so I didn't really plan to get on this
in this episode and and in fact we may
do an entire show on just fatigue
management sometime down the road
perhaps in season two or three we'll see
and so but I I got to give you a teaser
here and really to reiterate it's not
lactate that causes a fatigue but pH can
be a legitimate issue in our cardiac
episodes and some of the other ones that
we've done in this season on endurance I
have talked about when you exercise
fatigue is a global event there are what
do we call Central reasons for fatigue
so this is the central nervous system
this is the heart and cardiovascular
system and ability to move oxygen
throughout the body etc etc and they're
all peripheral issues more specific to
muscle uptake and oxygen as I said the
very beginning it is clear at this point
lack of oxygen in muscle is not the
cause of lactate production that part is
extraordinarily clear I think it's also
fair at this point while people are
debating still whether or not fatigue is
Central or perectly driven I think it's
hard in my opinion to make a reasonable
argument that it's not a combination of
both there are excellent review papers
on this that cover dozens of different
explanations I would love to be able to
explain to you in one or two words what
the real culprit is that's just not the
case easy examples if you change an
alter pH with exercise I'm almost almost
exclusively talking about more acidic
could be more alkaline it would have
really the same effect but really it's
acidic you've made that
pyate you've then tried to convert that
into lactate or you have successfully
converted into
lactate either way you still have
hydrogen floating around when you take
ATP and you split it into ADP that
requires that goes through a process
called hydrolysis this still results in
hydrogen production and so no matter how
you slice it if you're Contracting
muscle you're going to generate hydrogen
that's going to make the environment
more acidic enzymes all of the enzymes
involved in Aerobic anerobic
phosphocreatine muscle contraction all
of those are going to have a problem in
excessive acidic environments same thing
with temperature changes we see
alterations in things like calcium
signaling so calcium is one of the
important minerals required for muscle
contraction that gets altered uh during
muscle fatigue the little environment or
organel inside your muscle called
sarcoplasmic reticulum what holds and
stores your calcium and releases it
becomes problematic there are issues
with magnesium magnesium then starts
taking the place where calcium should be
there and inhibiting it um so we see
single muscle fiber contractile problems
we see oxygen transportation problems we
see other issues associated with um ATP
pumps and sodium potassium pumps being
disregulated and changed and altered so
really the most fair and honest way way
to explain to you why you're getting
fatigued well I know it's not because of
lactate buildup that's true and it's
definitely not because of lactic acid
and for that matter lactic acid is not
even close to being responsible for your
muscles being sore the next day that has
nothing to do with the equation it's
definitely not involved however you can
still globally say acid buildup that's a
reasonable thing to say it is more
complicated than that but it is also
true at the same time it's just probably
most appropriate decision while there is
an increased in acid buildup during
muscular fatigue it's not lactate
lactate is actually probably saving you
from acid buildup if that wasn't there
you'd have even more acidity but still
you see how those two things are going
to be highly Associated let's go back to
the very beginning hunted Stags imagine
you're running through a forest being
hunted or not doesn't matter but you're
exercising sprinting through there
you're creating more metabolic waste
more
pH more acid rather you're feeling more
fatigued at the same time you're having
a higher lack to e-lux even if that is a
positive thing for you those two things
increasing fatigue and increasing
lactate are going to be Associated and
that's why for almost 200 years of
lactate research we have Associated
fatigue with lactate buildup so they do
go hand inand but that is a classic
example of correlation not causation now
that we have a better understanding of
what lactate really is it's time for us
to discuss our three eyes such as how do
I investigate in other words how do I
measure my lactate or my lactate
threshold number two how do I interpret
it how much lactate should I have at
rest and what should my lactate
threshold be and what's the highest
lactates we've ever seen and then three
finally how do I intervene in other
words how do I improve my lacti
concentrations again at rest as well as
during exercise and then how will that
actually relate to my improvements in
sport performance let's get started with
the very beginning and that is
investigate so a couple ways to think
about this I slid in a term there I
realize I've said it a few times but
maybe not fully described and that is
lactate
threshold okay you can measure lactate
concentrations in your blood that's the
normal way to do it a biopsy is probably
not really sick for many of you and
honestly not necessary but I do want to
acknowledge a couple of things there are
a lot of lowcost lactate analyzers
available on the market when I was a
student you basically had to be an
exercise physiology lab now these are
consumer available for 20 to30 or
$40 there is also research on these
different devices and their accuracy and
they're not all the same I wish I had a
gold standard one I could say go buy
this one it is the best unfortunately
that's not the case honestly they
measure them a little bit differently
the techniques used the part of your
blood that's used is a little bit
different and so these values can be
fairly squirly I would strongly
encourage you to pick one and pick one
of ones from the research that is known
to be reliable and then use that for all
of your metrics moving forward if you
switch machines out and change
standardizations and procedures you're
going to get slightly different results
I will give you one little Insider tip
here behind the scenes if you're going
to use something like a small finger
stick or an earlobe stick which is the
most common ways to do
it that first drop of blood that comes
out I would wipe it away and not use it
it tends to give you really funky
numbers it's going to tell you the
lactate that is right there on that spot
rather than circulating in the tissue so
we always take the first couple drops
wipe them off and then use the second
ones you'll get much more reliable
numbers if not you will see your lactate
all over the place and you'll be like
what the heck is going on I don't
believe anything these people say about
exercise physiology because these
lactate numbers are totally screw so
that's going to tell you how much
lactate you have the other thing you
probably want to pay attention to is
what's called lactate threshold there
are at least 25 different methods I have
found in the literature for measuring
lactate threshold there is clearly no
succinct completely agreed upon method
many of them are good in fact all 20
five of those have been validated but
they are not measuring the same thing
this gets extraordinarily complicated
you thought that the biochemistry got
complicated earlier this is potentially
worse and it's not all measuring the
same thing generally the field has moved
past anob threshold you may have heard
of that before for the reasons I've
described we don't really talk about
that one however there is lactate
threshold and in fact there's multiple
stages of lactate threshold there's
stage one and stage two there's
ventilatory threshold and that is very
similar but it's not the same thing
there are things like critical power um
your maximum velocity at lactate
threshold your ability to sustain just
under lactate tal and a ton of different
things to pay attention to here so what
are you actually measuring is the first
question and then secondarily again
there are dozens of different free
lowcost and all the way up to clinical
research grade methods to assess lactate
threshold I'm not going to go through
all of them for you rather I want to arm
you with the tool of saying if you care
about learning something like your
lactate threshold that's great but
really pay attention to what your needs
are so what sport are you in are you a
distance Runner are a rower are you a a
more Anor robic sport athlete what are
you using and try to pick the test that
is best for you in your situation and
what do you care most about ventilatory
threshold anerobic threshold do you want
to know your race Pace that's probably
the most common reason people get a
lactate threshold test done is they want
to know what pace to run at uh during
their races or how fast they need to run
to be in zone one or two or three or
four how much time they should spend at
each exercise intensity and things like
that and so it is extremely context
dependent going through lactate
threshold I will give you a couple of
examples here but I did need to make
sure you understood
depending upon where you look you can
see wildly different numbers wildly
different protocols and dozens of
different free or in laboratory
assessment methods for lactate threshold
with that entire Preamble
aside even me trying to describe to you
what I mean by lactate threshold it's
different for each one of these
definitions quick example the general
idea here is we're trying to figure out
how fast can you run or how hard can you
row or cycle or whatever you're doing
before we see a different change in our
slope of lactate what do I mean imagine
you're sitting there at rest and you're
producing a very marginal but small
amount of lactate and now we start
jogging and then we slowly over the
course of say 10 to 30 minutes increase
our speed of jogging okay as I increase
my speed I'll increase my fatigue I'll
get more tired but that's not not a
linear increase it becomes exponential
it is linear at the bottom and then at
some point we have this sharp uptick and
fatigue now that is what we're trying to
identify as our lactate threshold what
we're saying is if I know that and let
me give you some numbers here let's say
you can run at 20 miles per hour that's
pretty darn fast it's not the fastest
ever but that's pretty fast and we'll
make numbers easy all right imagine you
and I both run at 20
mph and let's imagine just make it even
easier we have the same V2 Max so we
both have a V2 Max of 100 that would be
very very very high but I'm trying to
make math nice and easy for you so you
and I can both run 20 M hour and our V2
Max is 100 who's going to win the race
well if we look at Classic exercise
physiology literature there are three
main predictors of endurance performance
and again I really want you to think
about Marathon running just as an easy
example here your V2
Max your efficiency and your lactate
Thresh
what I've effectively saying is if you
and I both have the same V2 Max and the
same maximum running speed but you are
slightly more efficient than I am you
will have more energy to run that race
so even though we can run as fast as
each other you'll be able to run at a
higher percentage of your max speed
before you get tired this is classic
Jack Daniels not the the whiskey the the
famous running coach um has a ton of
work in this area in fact a lot of
people call him the greatest running
coach of all time I'm not a runner so I
don't know but he really laid this stuff
out and said all right if it's not those
two things it's your lactate threshold
so if both of us can run at 20 miles per
hour but you can run at
16 before your lactate really starts to
increase and I can run at 15 that means
in the race I have to run the race at
14.9 because if I go at 15 all of a
sudden I have this massive increase in
lactate and you get to go at 15.9 you
get to run a whole mile hour faster than
me even though our maximum speed is the
same and our V2 Max is the same so
lactate threshold is that way of saying
what's the threshold how much work can I
do how how many watts can I put out on
my bike before I have this again
excessive increase in in lactate buildup
why that matters not that lactate is
causing fatigue but that is clearly an
association which you have overwhelmed
mitochondria that's what it's telling
you mitochondria can no longer keep up
with lactate builds and now an e-lux
happens and this e-lux happens really
really fast easy easy examples to think
about go on and do some exercise at 80%
of your heart rate then do it at 85% and
do it at 90% you're going to feel slight
increases in fatigue go from 95% to 100
that 5% increase 95 to 100% will feel
way worse than if You' gone from 50 to
55% in fact you will feel very little
difference is in fatigue from 50 to 60
or
65% but a 10% increase going from 90 to
100 is way more fatiguing than going
from 50 to 60 hopefully that makes sense
and so fatigue is not linear like that
what we lactate threshold we're trying
to identify where do these breaking
points or what a lot of times we'll call
them as deflection points
happen well again this is where lactate
threshold gets complicated because
people Define these things differently
depending on the method you use and
again there's there's over 25 of them
there are excellent studies over the
last 30 years where you can take the
exact same report from the lab hand it
to different exercise physiologists and
get different lactate thresholds based
on calculation not only because of like
subjective decisions which can happen in
the visual method but also just which
calculation you're using which equation
you're using which method you're using
so a lot of the times um and I I'll get
to this in one second but just since
we're right here a lot of the times
people can say things like this all
right the visual method the most classic
method of lactate threshold
identification is you do a 30 to 60
Minute test and you slightly increase
fatigue over time and what you're going
to see is this slope of V2 so how much
oxygen you're using go up but again that
slope will have a big curve and there'll
be these inflection or deflection
points those points are then marked as
lactate Threshold at the very beginning
you tendency like an early one and then
there's a second one later so some
people say there's lactate threshold one
and threshold too others will say I
don't care about the first one I only
care about the second one it doesn't
matter it tends to be lactate um at and
we would have covered this in one second
but we'll do it now I guess since we're
here at rest your lactate is typically
something like 1 millimar maybe down to
0.5 millimar in that neighborhood and a
lot of people will then say lactate
threshold happens at two molar now you
may be familiar with that because that
is genely what people say as the thresh
threshold for being in zone two training
and that's exactly why one of the major
reasons people are excited about zone
two training is you're actually saying
we specifically staying below that
threshold which means we are not going
to overwhelm mitochondria we're going to
train them and work them but we're we're
not going to let them off the hook
because if we go too high we've bypassed
that system we're now having to deal
with so much lactate elux that we're
using different fuels of energy
production so we're going to stay right
below that threshold to make sure we put
the most pressure possible on
mitochondria this should enhance your
ability to use fat as a fuel source this
should enhance mitochondria biogenesis
and a bunch of other positive benefits
associated with that type of
training others are then going to say no
lactate threshold happens at four
millimolars it's a different thing but
there is a very clear distinction
between two and four and so in fact
probably the
most common way to establish lactate
threshold in science is to just
arbitrarily say what speed in the case
of running or wattage in the case of
cycling are you at when you hit four
millimolars of lactate and so rather
than defining it by the slope of that
oxygen increase and I know this is a
little bit Technical and wordy for some
folks a lot of times you can just
arbitrarily say it is four millimolar
and where you're at when you cross that
threshold is your lactate threshold
scientifically you will see equal
accuracy between both of those methods
now if you don't have the ability to
analyze lactate directly there are a
number of different ways to estimate it
I mentioned Jack Daniels earlier he has
by far the most popular version called a
v do this is a little bit of a play he
actually initially I think he called it
the pseudo V2 Max and they had this
really cool conversion equation uh for
this book's very very old but it's
really cool and it allows you to say all
right if you know your race pace so
whether you've done a 400 meter dash 800
met Dash either way up to a marathon
half marathon on 5Ks 10ks any one of
these races you can actually look up
your race score in it he's got all kinds
of tables these are available all over
the Internet and then you can look and
predict your performance in any of those
other races based on your V do which is
really pretty cool actually and so you
get an idea of how much time you should
be spending in each training Zone
according at least to to Dr Jack but
that is is a nice way to do it is it
perfect no is it scientifically
validated yeah so pretty cool tool there
if you want to know more about your race
Pace if you have the data from one you
can predict it and many others if you
want you can go to the show notes and
pull up the papers and these exact
tables and look up your scores but I'll
give you a couple just since we're here
to have a little bit of fun let's take
uh mile most people know their mile time
and you probably think back to high
school fact you should go run one right
now and see where you're at I always
think like once a year you should go run
a mile and see where you're at uh okay
so let's just pick a random score here
let's say you ran a mile in 7 minutes
and 38 seconds according to this table
then you should be able to run a uh 10K
in 53 minutes or so a half marathon in
an hour and 58 minutes and a full
marathon in 4 hours and 4 minutes if
you've ever done any of those events
that smells pretty good right you're
running a 7 and a half minute 8 minute
mile recreational Runners that go run a
marathon probably going to do a 4-Hour
Marathon those numbers again are pretty
good if we want to have a little more
fun for those of you faster out there
let's say you have a V2 Max of 70 ml per
kilogram per minute is um more
specifically technically V Dot of 70 but
those are somewhat interchangeable here
this should mean you should be able to
do a one M race in 4 minutes and 19
seconds which is cruising not elite
elite but pretty Elite for most people
also a 70 ml per kilogram per minute V2
Max is pretty Elite so that makes sense
your 10K time would be 31 minutes your
half marathon would be 1 hour and 8
minutes and your full Marathon would be
2 hours and 23 minutes again feels
pretty darn good let's go even further
all the way down let's just keep that
same person just to do a couple more
ones um if you wanted to do kind of uh
interval pacing you'd run a 400 meter
dash in 71 seconds which again feels
about right and a 200 meter dash in 32
seconds and so there again you can look
up any one of these and and there's
bunch of them if you want to look up
your marathon pace your easy uh running
pace your threshold Pace your interval
Pace your repetition Pace they're all
available in these uh gez I don't know
30 40 50 year old charts at this point I
can just tell you anecdotally spending
many many years in exercise physiology
Labs with a lot of endurance athletes
though I'm not one myself and these
numbers are pretty good I've yet to find
anybody who's significantly off on them
you'll have some people who are just a
little bit unique but they're they're
pretty darn good and pretty impressive
uh to figure all this stuff out without
the Advanced Technologies we have now I
know we got a little bit off track there
but to wrap up the investigation if you
want to know your lactate levels a
lactate analyzer is really the only way
to do it but really pay attention get a
high quality one and use the same one
over and over if you want to know your
lactate threshold you have dozens of
ways to do it the gold standard is to go
into a laboratory
at this point it's somewhere usually
between1 and $200 or so to find a lab
that has a metabolic cart now not all
offer a lactate threshold test but if
they do that's probably what you're
going to be looking at they tend to last
something like 30 to 60 Minutes you're
going to have to run for a long time and
is a lot different than a V2 Max s so if
you specifically want a lactate
threshold test you need to ask for that
not nearly as many Labs offer that as a
VO2 max test in the VO2 max test some
some will take your lactate but that's
not a true lactate threshold test that's
a very different thing um usually what
we're looking at here is something like
four to five minute stages where we
slightly increase the velocity on the
treadmill or something like that and
we're going to take a a finger or ear
stick and plot out your lactate every
four minutes for like I said 30 to 60
minutes so that is the kind of the gold
standard if you really want to know if
not there are tons of ways there's
concone test there are 30 minute run
tests there are two mile tests there's
Jack Daniels tables and a bunch of other
ways you can just take a heart rate
monitor at most at least a stopwatch go
run a test come back with your numbers
plug it in and get a good sense of your
lactate threshold hopefully though in a
few years we'll have a better answer for
this I know of at least four companies
at this point who are working on
continuous lactate monitors these come
in the form of watches as well as an
eyepiece like a contact lens that can do
that that technology is already
available for things like like glucose
monitoring and I know that many
companies again are working on this for
lactate I don't know exactly when
they'll be on the market but I would
imagine potentially by the time you're
even listening to this they're available
if not pretty soon after that I don't
know the accuracy or validity of them of
course that will come in time but it's
reasonable to think it's not a
particularly hard thing to measure it is
needed in so many different areas even
things like acute medicine and Trauma
heart failure heart attacks other issues
like that so I am pretty optimistic that
within a few years there will be really
highquality continuous lactate analyzers
available to the masses I mentioned this
just a second ago but it's worth
repeating in terms of interpreting these
data at rest something like one Millar
of lactate is pretty normal maybe even
down to 0.5 what I can tell you and this
is just anecdote this is Andy's personal
coaching belief you will not find
extensive data to support this we know
lactate at Baseline is a reflection of
what's happening in your mitochondri and
since you're not going through much
physical activity there shouldn't be
much now we don't want it to be zero
because the lactate is beneficial it is
good but I think my interpretation of it
is this gives you tremendous insight
about your metabolic
flexibility if somebody has a resting
lactate of 1.5 or even honestly in like
1.2
1.3 I have seen this often times
associated with either short-term
overtraining or overreaching
excessive stress psychological or
physiological other things going on in
their blood work with hydration number
of cortisol disregulation and things
like that also could indicate a bias
towards carbohydrate metabolism so this
is actually something that is a little
bit sneaky I don't want you to be to
over interpret yourself there there is
actually some data on what happens I
know that least there's some case
studies on individual athletes
throughout the entire year of the season
and when they're doing more lower
intensity endurance work resting lactate
levels come down and when they shift
over to more power and speed and Peak
Performance they start to go up this
makes sense we know that physiological
adaptations happen in the muscle when
you bias towards different forms of
energy production it's a good thing
right and so that's actually one of the
things I pay attention to as a idea of
to see okay is this person struggling
with fat utilization I should be able to
use a lot of fat as a fuel source at
rest and so therefore lactate production
should be fairly minimal and so
something to keep in mind like I said
said once you get to two or so you
probably feel different so if you're at
that stage you may actually have
something else going on that's medical
diabetes or metabolic acidosis or
something like that I don't know again
I'm not a doctor don't use me for
medical advice but the point is
somewhere around one or so is normal at
maximal exercise you will see people get
as high as 20 to 25 I don't know what
the highest number I've ever really seen
is I know of some folks in medical
situations uh like having metabolic
acidosis It's associated with diabetes
especially at altitude highest number
I've seen in literature is like 47
millimar I know of a group of actually
endurance athletes who supposedly
maintained 10 millimolar for an hour
straight which again folks some people
will be peing at 10 Michael Phelps
supposedly only got to eight even during
world record um swim performances right
fatiguing not the not the Sprint ones
and so a lot of high level athletes 10
12 is enough some can get up to 20
25 and in that particular case that
person was up to 47 which is
extraordinarily High I don't know what
the real numbers are for that but that
gives you a little bit of context of
where you're at at rest as well as
maximal exercise in terms of lactate
threshold typically happens around 70%
or so of your V2 Max or maximum heart
rate um for recreationally or lightly
trained individuals as you become more
physically fit and you're able to handle
that e-lux better for a number of
different reasons you're either better
at creating lactate or you're better at
clearing it then that number actually
gets higher it's not uncommon to see
folks high 70s 80s even up to 85% um we
don't have a ton of data on male versus
female but the stum that is available
suggests it's slightly higher in women
than it is in men but I wouldn't say
that that is a complete slam dunk in the
science um you will often also see this
number to vary between highly successful
individuals like I said earlier
endurance events can have success in
many different ways so you can have a
higher V2 Max you can have a higher
running economy or cycling or swimming
economy or you can have a higher lactate
threshold but at the same token that
also means you can be really good with a
lower lactate threshold so there's a lot
of paths to victory in sports and
endurance is no different so anything in
that Stratosphere of kind of 80 85% uh
would be normal for a moderate to
decently train endurance athlete fun
fact while we're on this point remember
the heart itself needs metabolism so it
is going through energy production it is
then therefore generating lactate as a
byproduct of its own endogenous energy
production so the energy needed for the
heart to contract now if you give a
given second typically when your hard is
Contracting that takes around 200
milliseconds and around 800 of the
milliseconds then are left with the
hardest not Contracting so it's filling
back up with blood it's thought then
that during that contraction time you're
producing lactate during the relaxation
time which is again four times as long
it's clearing the lactate but once heart
rate gets really really high and that
goes from a 4 to one relax to contract
ratio to 3:1 to 2:1 to 1: one or even
more than that the heart doesn't
actually have enough time to clear all
of its own endogenous lactate production
which is one of the reasons why you
become fatigued which brings us to our
final eye intervene a handful of ways
you want to think about this number one
you want to make sure you're
metabolically flexible so that we're not
creating too much lactate at rest and
not too little as well we talked about
possible supplementation directly of
lactate and that doesn't seem to be
panning out at this particular point
maybe more hope for gels and creams but
as a direct supplement doesn't seem to
be super effective
nutritionally well you might think about
carbohydrates are important important
and the primary place of which lactate
created so then should I have lower
carbohydrates or should I have more
carbohydrates at this point I don't
think there's any specific rationale to
think as long as metabolic flexibility
is appropriate that increasing or
decreasing carbohydrates is going to
play significant role in your quality of
lactate management will it change
production look anytime you have more
carbohydrates especially directly prior
to exercise you're going to bias
carbohydrate metabolism which is a way
of saying you will shift more of your
energy coming from carbohydrates because
more is acutely available so will that
shift and alter lactate production
potentially but is that making a
meaningful impact on human performance
well outside of the benefits of having
carbohydrates in your system it's
unclear at this point in terms of
training then all we really have to
think about is what's going to advance
and increase mitochondrial Health
quantity and size in the reality of it
is you have a ton of options here we
talked about this a lot in our other
episodes on the heart and V2 Max and so
I'll keep it brief here you can head
over there for more detail but you have
different options what about low
intensity exercise what about zone two
well let's run the whole gamut here
starting off with low intensity exercise
we know that zone one or zone two can
enhance mitochondria quality this is
almost by definition staying at 2
millimoles or lower so that's absolutely
a strategy in fact many distance and
endurance coaches are going to spend a
lot if not most of their time in that
area and for probably very good reasons
if that also increases capillarization
and we're able to then get out lactate
of the muscle and get it spread across
to the other tissue the heart the liver
the kidneys the brain then that's going
to be effective what about more moderate
continuous exercise in the research we
generally abbreviate this as miic so
moderate intensity continuous
training well that works too now you're
probably in the neighborhood of 2 to
four millars something like that and
you're going to be doing it for a longer
duration is it having the exact same
effects no but has it been shown many
many times to enhance mitochondria
quality fuel utilization and waste
removal
absolutely continuing past that what
about higher intensity stuff really now
we're talking about a couple of things
high-intensity intervals is a good way
to do it and you can do these in long or
short the short version would be
something like 20 to 90 seconds of a
burst followed by one: one or up to 3 to
one rest so this could be as short as 30
seconds of rest up to even 3 minutes or
more of rest also incredibly effective
we know this increases VO2 max and
certainly lactate threshold as well as
overall economy so another possible
strategy the longer duration intervals
would be more like 2 3 4 up to 5 minutes
with an equal or larger amount of rest
this is a classic most well described
one four minutes of allout work matched
by 4 minutes of
rest important to realize when I say
things like that four minutes of all out
work I really don't truly mean that you
can't be at 100% of your V2 Max for 4
minutes typically high-intensity
interval training is really honestly
somewhere between 85 to 90 maybe up to
95% and so good but a slightly different
mechanism the highest on the end here
then past that is what we usually call S
or Sprint interval training and now this
is truly at 100 if not higher or super
maximum allout exercise the duration
here is far shorter sometimes as low as
even like 10 to 15 second bursts matched
by a lot of rest but now you got to
repeat this many many times so instead
of doing things like uh 30 seconds on 30
seconds off for say four attempts or
five attempts or even your longer
duration ones for again three or four
you're doing many more maybe up to 20
repetitions if not more than that of
these short bursts if you look at the
research and the studies even the met
analyses that have directly compared
MCTS moderate intensity stuff with low
intensity stuff maybe even
high-intensity intervals and sits and
there's lots of different combinations
in the research here you're going to
find slight differences I'll acknowledge
that but all of them
work do they have unique components to
it I think so I don't think we have a
ton of information to explicitly say
that with confidence because again they
all generally work now sometimes in some
studies and some met analyses some work
slightly better than others for
different aspects and so to me the clear
answer is you should probably have all
of it in your program there should be
plenty of time at low intensity steady
state sub 2 millimolar sometime they'll
probably not a ton but sometime in two
to four millimolar range continuous
submaximal stuff a decent amount of time
in these higher 85 to 95% high-intensity
interval ranges and then some small
amount of time in the super maximal but
the final Point here is
this remember fatigue exists on a
nonlinear curve and so if you can
imagine all four of these paradigms on
that curve if I'm in zone one or two and
I double my work I go twice as fast I
only have a small increase in fatigue as
long as I'm still in that zone going
from 40% to 55%
is not much more fatiguing but as I go
and I cross miic and I get into the high
intense intervals now two three four 5%
increases have huge increases in fatigue
and now I get all the way up to Super
maximal I have large increases in
fatigue for very small increases in
performance to me that suggests you
should probably spend small amounts of
time in the top end of the
range some amount of time in the middle
and then a lot or or most of your time
in the low end of the
range rationale not
being low intensity is more effective it
clearly is not I need to repeat that low
intensity is not more effective at
improving V2 Max it is not more
effective at Fat Loss which we've talked
about in other episodes it is not more
effective at improving
mitochondria it is
however more
recoverable at the same time it takes a
long time and so the benefit B of going
at moderate and high and even really
high intensities is they're really
really short I don't need to be running
for 45 or 60 minutes and they are
providing unique and potentially
potentially more
adaptations I just can't spend all my
time doing that because I won't have the
recovery necessary to keep it up for
long enough to really get sustained
adaptations so in my opinion whether
you're in this for sport performance you
want to run a Marathon you want to row
in a race you want to do a Iron Man or
whether you're in this for life you just
want to improve your V2 Max you want to
enhance your metabolic flexibility
improve your overall mitochondrial
Health have more energy throughout the
day more Global recovery be better at
utilizing all forms of fuel the answer
at the end of the day is still the same
you probably want to train over that
full spectrum making sure we lower or at
least keep our lactate production at
Baseline
moderate to low enhancing our lactate
threshold enhancing our total ability to
produce to generate and to handle and
clear lactate once it's there
appreciating all the benefit it's doing
for our memory for our brain health for
our cognition for our heart for our
liver for our wound healing for our
immune system for our digestive system
and everything else that lactate is
doing to make us a healthier happier and
better performing human thank you for
joining for today's episode our goal is
to share exciting scientific Insight
that helps you perform at your absolute
best if the show resonates with you and
you want to help ensure this information
remains free and accessible to anyone in
the world there are a few ways that you
can support first you can subscribe to
the show on YouTube Spotify and apple
and on Apple and Spotify you can leave
up to a fstar review given that we're a
new podcast subscribing and leaving a
review really does help us a lot second
please check out our sponsors the show
would not exist without them and they
really are exceptional products and
services and then finally you can share
today's episode with a friend who you
think would enjoy it if you have any
content questions or suggestions please
put those in the comment section on
YouTube I really do try to read these
and see what you have to say if you have
yet to sign up for our monthly
newsletter you can do so at perform
podcast.com our newsletter provides
episode summaries with the key takeaways
for each and every episode of the
podcast this includes topics like how to
improve your VO2 max how to build muscle
mass and muscle strength how to optimize
your sleep for high performance and much
more to sign up just go to perform
podcast.com click newsletter at the top
of the screen and then enter your email
address once you sign up you receive
access to all of our newsletters I use
my Instagram and Twitter also
exclusively for scientific communication
so those are great places to follow
along for more learning my handle is Dr
Andy Galpin on both platforms thank you
for listening and never forget in the
famous words of Bill Bowerman if you
have a body you're an athlete